[Music]
Charles it's really good to speak to you
again we put out a piece with you about
a month ago called an epidemic of
control that seems to have done really
well since we put that out I've been
working quite a lot on initially stories
to do with the David Icke appearance on
London real and to issues to do with
particularly free speech censorship and
conspiracy theory and as I was working
on it you brought out another piece
called the conspiracy myth and you
echoed so many of the pieces that I was
that I've been thinking about been
writing about being making a film about
so I really wanted to get you on and
maybe we can kind of explore some of
these topics together but firstly just
because I know that people that this is
a topic that people get very exercised
about get very energized about I think
well let's start by unpacking what you
mean by the conspiracy myth because I
think people might kind of react to that
in some way right generally people react
to it with either a big sigh of relief
that I'm not one of those conspiracy
people because Here I am calling it a
myth or with indignation because now I'm
smearing them with this epithet of
conspiracy theorists which was in fact
well who knows what a fact is but was in
fact invented by the CIA CIA to
discredit people who disagreed with the
warren commission's verdict on the
kennedy assassination
so yeah really good question what do I
mean by the conspiracy myth what I mean
by a myth is very different than what I
mean by a fantasy or delusion I think
the key point is that by calling a myth
you're not saying that it's untrue
that's right I mean we right I'm saying
oh yeah I'm saying that it's true but
the truth may not be the literal truth
it reminds me very much of the
evolutionary biologist Brett Weinstein's
comment about religion being literally
false but metaphorically true and I'm
Jordan Pederson also talking about myths
being almost hyper true or hyper hyper
objects in some way right yes I would I
would agree with that with that
understanding of it with the caveat
that the whole idea of literally true is
itself based on a myth and the myth
being the myth of objectivity the
understanding that it's a certain
narration of what the universe is and
our relationship to it that there is a
subjective reality outside of ourselves
that is unaffected by our story making
that that the results of experiments are
unaffected by the kind of experiment and
the intention with which we go into that
experiment so so if you discard that
myth then you know then you've opened
Pandora's box which that would be like a
whole conversation in and of itself but
yeah like our last conversation the
epidemic of control that from the
conspiracy myth and this is another
illustration of what I mean by it from
the conspiracy myth the the conclusion
is ah there must be somebody in somebody
in control somebody controlling us let's
find those people and do what ultimately
control them so in a way the conspiracy
myth is part of the epidemic of control
it's just identifying the controlling
force as a group of conspirators and so
in in the essay when I what I really
meant by conspiracy myth is is like this
arch arch theory that the whole world
that the workings of the world can be
fundamentally explained by conspiracy
there's somebody behind the scenes
pulling the strings and that explains
everything yeah this is such an
important distinction and I think I
don't know if we even have language to
express it because there seems to me to
be such a qualitative difference between
conspiracy hypothesis which a lot of
turned out to be true from MKULTRA to
until pro and we've put out films on our
channel about the Epstein case like that
looks very much like some kind of big
structure that Epstein was just the
frontman for those sort of things like
whenever we talk about conspiracy theory
once we roll those two things together
we're in a very difficult place but I
think there is a qualitative difference
between alternative histories collusion
corruption and what feels to me and I
think we need to bring in some kind of
mythopoetic or religious dimension to
understand the latter which is this
sense of an all-powerful force how do
you differentiate because that for me is
one of the central problems in talking
about this is we're rolling it's I think
scientists call it an overloaded turn so
conspiracy theory is such an overloaded
turn that it's very difficult to pull
apart and talk about right yeah I mean
mostly it's a term of derision and I was
really like I'm actually even in this
conversation I'm noticing what tone of
voice do I adopt when I said the idea
that you know a group of evil puppet
masks I'm not sure what I said but
something like the idea that a group of
evil puppet masters are pulling the
strings and who are and they're actually
in control of the world did I say that
within neutral turn a neutral tone or
did I say that with a derisive tone if I
say it with a derisive tone guess what
I'm doing I am joining the playground
bullies and gaining acceptance by
displaying the correct attitude of the
in-group and I wonder so it's not and I
wonder if you like I read your essay as
well um which I very much appreciated
for its nuance actually but I wonder if
like if you have that impulse sometimes
and if you're aware of that impulse to
kind of establish your legitimacy by
criticizing those who are even farther
out on the fringes than you are because
I've been you know aware of that
tendency in myself
yeah but I do wonder if it's possible to
to talk about these things from a
completely neutral place at all I mean
I've tried to be careful with my
language while talking about like there
is for example you can talk about and I
have sort of fringe medical figures but
I've tried hard to talk about it in the
context of saying fringe by definition
not part of the mainstream conversation
but I've also tried to frame it as a way
by saying we don't know if this is
actually valuable information like there
have been people that have been medical
figures coming out and saying for
example the doctor in New York I quoted
he said this doesn't look like you know
pneumonia this looks like altitude
sickness and that then 2-3 weeks later
was then incorporated into our
understanding of the disease so I'm
trying to talk about this but even using
the word fringe for some people that's
that's kind of you're you're loading
your terms you're pushing people out of
the conversation so I I don't know if
it's possible to use language accurately
and not do that in some way I think
you're right I think that the ideal of
impartiality is actually impossible
because it it almost by definition it's
like okay I'm gonna stand on the solid
ground but nobody even agrees on what
the solid ground is there's no consensus
about what constitutes a legitimate fact
and where legitimate facts are to be
sourced from
so it's it's I think as long as we
recognize that then at least we have the
potential to be aware of our biases and
even that is is a process of progressive
uncover II said a word
no uncovering discovery and and not an
ideal that we could ever reach and
that's the end of like III want people
to be more generous in their and their
listening to people who disagree with
them because the the tendency in such a
highly polarized time is to cast them
into the ranks of the Damned of the you
know Covidien
or of the sheeple you know or of the
propaganda matrix or whatever like
institutions are not monolithic there's
if you even look at even if you're a
fierce critic of the WH o or the CDC if
you're not recognizing that there are
actually within that organization many
maybe even a majority of sincere ethical
caring people then you will never
understand that organization and you
will never understand why they appear to
be part of a conspiracy because because
it's really about the culture of the
institution and the environment that
they operate in just gonna butt in and
say that I think my the most persuasive
explanation that I've heard of that kind
of the institutional decay that I think
has happened to a lot of our
institutions we put out a film with with
Eric Weinstein talking about how since
the 1980s what a lot of these
institutions have done have effectively
once you politicize an institution you
take it away from its main from its main
function you get people jockeying for
hierarchy within it for reasons other
than that they're good at doing the
thing that our institution is is
designed for I think there's some sense
see there
this is actually an interesting parallel
because I think that's that's the felt
sense that I think a lot of people are
picking up and that's why I think that's
what I think the metaphorical truth of a
lot of the conspiracy by the overarching
conspiracy narratives are is that we are
we have these some very very deeply
corrupt fragile hollow systems and you
look for example I look at the wire
David Simon's the wire which he called a
meditation on the death of America where
he looked at like what happened to the
police force when you're basically just
trying to meet the stats rather than to
do your job the parallels between the
police and the drug gangs you get
trapped in these systems of incentive
structures and essentially and then he
looked at the media he looked at
teaching you look to all of these
different systems and say
they're all kind of being hollowed out
at the same time and my sense is we my
sense is that this is what people are
picking up on a real felt sense level
that something is deeply off in society
and it's not too it's not too big a leap
to say okay well who is doing this and
who is who is gaining from this i
totally resonate with that that that the
conspiracy myth comes from a very
authentic accurate perception that our
institutions have betrayed us that
they're not serving their declared
interests that they have a secret agenda
that they are the puppets of something
personally i don't think that that they
are the puppets of a group of evil
conspirators i think it's more accurate
to say that they're the puppets of a
paradigm of a mythology of a set of
interests of a system of an economic
system of an ideology of control you
know that this is what i wrote about in
the other essay you know that that
civilization defines progress as the
increase in our ability to impose
control upon the world and to control
the other to control matter to control
society to control the barbarians the
terrorists the weeds the bugs the
bacteria etc etc so if we are immersed
in that world view then we're going to
it's going to look like something is
coordinating everybody toward a goal of
more and more control or if you have say
it's like more mundane lis if you have a
system that's set up a medical research
system that is funded at bottom in large
part by pharmaceutical corporations who
make money by patenting drugs then
you're gonna have a lot of money
available to study patentable things and
you're gonna have and that money will
will have infused the entire system
that if you're a graduate student
looking for a good research project
those of you the ones that are available
and that'll be the kind of learning that
will be applicable to something that
advances your career so it's not that
you know you're in the in the pay of
nefarious powers and you're this venal
corrupt fake scientist who's just in it
for the money it's like that's the whole
cast of the system like I don't want to
say that it's conspiracies never
happened I mean they suppress
information like that happens look at
Vioxx so so I'm not like I'm not like
being Pollyanna here and saying oh they
would never ever do something that
corrupt they do things that corrupt I
think that but but I think more often
it's unconscious in systemic which means
that you'll never solve the problem by
removing the bad actors yeah my friend
Peter I think he said something like
becoming we all have to become
conspiracy theorists or some kind of
initiation mm-hmm that it's part of a
kind of world initiation like and we
have to obviously we have to question
consensus reality and I think those of
us who've been in sort of what you don't
have a better word than spiritual
communities to kind of to go with that
but those of us who've been in those
kind of communities questioning
consensus reality is is such an
important part of that and awakening to
something deeper and awakening to some
deeper sense of what humanity is and
what our potentials are but then I guess
that struggle as difficulty is not to
collapse into another fixed narrative on
the other side of that awakening which
is what I've seen a lot of can happen
very easily once we've had those
experiences we can have a kind of
shattering an old world view but what we
often do is we reform an equally solid
world view around some new material that
then just kind of it's part of the same
problem in a way rather than allowing
ourselves to remain open to uncertainty
and an open
to the journey totally and often that
new world view is actually the old world
view in coded form it's just a different
form of the same thing and the real
initiation or like maybe I'll say
another stage of the initiation is you
you you go from the default consensus
reality to you know a conspiracy theory
or a cult you know it could be anything
that's that's the receiving room for
people who have left the old story and
then you're like actually that's not
working either like that has some of the
same limitations and so you go to
another one another one and that process
is the is is it's a series of stepping
stones into the unknown into the place
of being comfortable with uncertainty
and looking at the parts of you that
yeah that you've kept at bay by offering
them certainty what comes up when you
allow yourself to be in uncertainty when
you allow yourself not to know that one
that requires undoing some pretty deep
programming in our school system for
example you're rewarded for knowing
you're rewarded for producing the
correct answer not knowing is that's
that's a new habit and we have an entire
scientific ideology that says that that
humanity is converging closer and closer
to the literal objective truth that we
are approaching a theory of everything
of the universe and a technological
system that that says once we order and
fix a number to each object in the world
and each person in the world we convert
everything into data then we will be
able to rationally and optimally manage
this world so this this prejudice toward
knowing and the punishments we've
received for not knowing these these
constitute a deep programming that
really takes some courage and some
community to undo to be okay with maybe
nobody knows and it's okay not to know
for a while I really like that Charles
because it it seems that that's one of
the failure conditions right now of
politics of journalism as of all these
different areas is this people who are
claiming to know things like this air of
certainty that everyone seems to be
coming in with and it's just falling
apart it's just being obviously
challenged because especially under the
influence or impact of so much novelty
that we're seeing with the pandemic
anyone who's in a public any kind of
public role who is claiming certainty
and they they sort of claim certainty
like a kind of defensive posture
everyone is starting to see through that
now and it feels like that particular
mentality is is what we're seeing being
tested to destruction right now it's the
affectation like I come from from the
traditional media and I think that more
than anything is what people pick up on
um really distrust is this sense of the
voice from nowhere this sense of instant
expertise on a subject that probably the
journalist has just started researching
that morning all of those things like
that air of defensive certainty just
seems to be something that's being that
that to me is like right at the core of
what's being undermined and dissolving
right now yeah especially when it comes
from the elites from from you know
people with in positions of social
authority because I think with very very
good reason over the last few decades
people have been in growing distrust of
the elites and if their arrogance
you know if our society has had
continued to improve you know from the
post-world War two ERA then maybe we
would trust our elites if if you know
the ecology of the planet were healing
getting better if social inequality
we're improving if if people's
psychological health were improving if
people's physical health were improving
if our social ills were dwindling for
the last 30 years we would probably
trust our elites and their
pronouncements of what is good for us
but none of these things have been
happening instead we've seen growing
inequality growing insecurity growing
psychological distress depression
anxiety declining health autoimmunity
addiction no no so somebody comes in and
says listen to us we have your best
interests at heart and we know what
we're doing our lived experience does
not confirm that in the way that it
might have in 1965 well I think is I
think that centrally important to
recognize where we are thinking in
religious terms and how frequently we're
thinking in religious kind of
mythological language because my sense
is with with the most again we come to
this problem with with terminology but
what I'm thinking about kind of
all-encompassing conspiracy theories for
example David Icke talks about a
murderous cult who are running
everything you have qyn on and the Cabal
like those for me feel qualitatively
whatever the word is the sort of it all
encompassing religious narrative they're
in on this side of it what I find really
fascinating about those is that even
though you could argue that there's very
dark material in there there's kind of
the idea of sort of evil evil cult evil
small groups of people they're actually
wrapped your ideologies
because they're saying if only we could
expose this defined group of people then
the better world is just the other side
of that if we could only only kind of
overthrow the Cabal if we could only
expose this evil cult and it could have
today it could happen tomorrow utopia is
at hand like the deep Christian roots of
a worldview like that I think have to be
really made explicit and and seen for
what it is because I'd like if only the
world was that simple if only it was
that easy to achieve utopia
totally I mean that's a perfect example
of the new story being actually the old
story in different form the old story
being progress through the conquest of
evil the conspiracy narrative is very
much the same you know it's we're gonna
expose the core of evil and overthrow it
and a better world paradise will be at
hand the dominant story is the same evil
taking the guise of chaos of the wild of
the the you know the germs the
unruliness of nature the natural forces
that are indifferent to human well-being
that was in fact the the concept of evil
was originally associated with chaos and
the wild there are like ancient Sumerian
inscriptions to this effect but that you
know the good king goes out and conquers
the barbarians drains the wetlands cuts
down the forests slays the wild beasts
who are become like the wolf the big bad
wolf they are evil and the Sheep is good
the weeds are evil the corn is good the
barbarians are evil
the civilized people are good that's
where evil came from as a concept so so
and and it and it leads to an ideology
of progress through domination because
we're always good you know and they're
evil so yeah it mutates into conspiracy
theory but in my view that's not
actually a very fundamental revolution
it's still exploring the territory of
separation of
troll and and to molt beyond that you
have to go through the territory of
again unknowing so yeah I think that's
very perceptive David that um you know
the the coded judeo-christian dimension
to their conspiracy theories I wondered
whether you also get the sense that this
kind I don't know if it's a new
phenomenon but it certainly seems to
have accelerated under the under the
kind of impact of the pandemic of
spiritual communities new age
communities like it's very difficult
nowadays to see to kind of tell where
some kind of all-encompassing conspiracy
narrative has come from whether it's
come from sort of the more traditionally
kind of pro-trump
right-wing sources or it could have come
from sort of more left weighing natural
news New Age places but there seems to
be this coming together of the of these
narratives in a really strange way if
you noticed that accelerates I can't
tell right from left anymore I mean I
thought it was supposed to be the
leftists that were eating organic food
and using natural medicine and who doing
home births and saying question
authority don't trust the man and and
now all of that in the in the context of
coded that's being associated with the
right wing I'm like hold on I thought it
was the left that was supposed to doubt
Authority and rebel and stuff so it's
it's on the bright side I think that
this is pointing through the possibility
of a new populism an authentic populism
that transcends current political
categories and that would draw from both
the left and the right from the
anarchists and the libertarians that
basically it's the people who are
defecting from the the establishment
from various forms of orthodoxy for you
know and on the other side are the
people who are who are still bought
to the orthodoxy and again like this is
actually to black and white a picture
because almost everybody I know is a
rebel in some ways and unconsciously
Orthodox in other ways so this is not
actually an us-versus-them this is a
process that every person on earth is is
going through this it's an inner an
inner split or an inner indeterminacy
which side am I on
actually maybe the reason that people
are so hostile to those on the other
side is because the other side
represents a shadow part of themselves
that they're afraid of like there are
I'm sure that the most viciously
Orthodox person harbors an inner rebel
that is being suppressed harbors part of
them that actually does doubt everything
that they themselves are saying and the
that the fear of that suppressed part
it's actually pretty justified because
that will tear your life apart it will
tear your identity apartment if you have
identified with being right and if your
position in society depends on you being
right and depends on this whole
worldview being right then the heterodox
positions the dissenting narratives
these are a literal threat to your
identity so how how welcome almost it is
to have somebody like David Icke as the
projection screen for these suppressed
shadow rebellious parts that can then be
ridiculed and attacked and the more
ridiculous he is the better the better
he serves that purpose so you see the
the guardians of the orthodoxy
cherry-picking the most ridiculous
of conspiracy theories in order to debt
to demonstrate the unacceptability of
what's actually in themselves as well
yeah that's an interesting comparison I
mean I obviously that the article that I
wrote talked about David I talked about
David Icke in the context of the London
real interview but I also have this
sense that David Icke should be part of
the conversation he's been saying he's
been saying what he's been saying for a
very long time and I don't get the sense
with for example with someone like Alex
Jones who seems to kind of I don't get
the sense that he believes a lot of the
stuff that he's saying he's following
whatever the audience is wanting
conspiracy is entertainment David Icke
has been kind of true to his stuck to
his guns for about thirty years and I
don't think he can be kept out he can be
kind of gate keep gate heaped gate kept
out of the conversation in the way that
he has been in the cast yeah totally
part of me resonates with it let me say
like part of me feels almost a sense of
relief at the idea that there is this
Luciferian cult that controls the world
and standing behind them negative aliens
and demonic beings the part of me that
breathes a sigh of relief is the part
that then can understand it makes sense
of the world not being able to make
sense of the world is stressful we're
especially in this civilization that's
so predicated on control so what David
Icke offers is is a sense making
narrative that delivers people from the
uncomfortable state of uncertainty but I
think actually what we need is to stay
in the uncertainty even more that said
you know so so basically so I am weary
of the part of me that wants to leap
into a new sense a new meaning a new
story to replace the one that I grew up
in
the conventional one you know where well
ma'am I'm not going to try to recite it
however another thing though is that
that a lot of the data points that he
weaves into his narrative deserve
attention there are lower level
conspiracies that actually like we were
saying like that
conspiracies actually do happen and
governments lie corporations lie we have
no one should have any doubt that that
happens and and to look into the
possibility that the extent of their
line could be a lot bigger than the ones
that we found out about and David Icke
brings light to some of those things and
that and and helps helps like another
positive thing that he's doing is he's
he's offering people and expanded
reality our art our world's problems are
actually technically easy to solve if
only we expanded the scope of of what we
understand to be a legitimate solution
if we expanded medicine to include all
of the holistic and alternative
medicines that I mean I know from
firsthand experience secondhand
experience that they work and there's
even a lot of scientific research like
artemisia annua is is is a
well-established anti-malarial drug and
it's the mechanism by which it
interferes with blood-borne viruses I
can't actually remember I don't I don't
want to pretend to be scientific here
but there's there's a lot of science
behind it let me just say that so like
there's there's so many data points and
I don't know like personally if you've
experienced things in your own life that
the dominant story of the world encoded
in science says are impossible I have so
and many people have like people have
experienced in
precognitive dreams and psychic
phenomena and mystical experiences and
anomalous healings and just like like
like incredible synchronicities that
blow your mind
and I think that and experiences with
indigenous people and those kinds of
technologies I think we need to bring
that in I think that our our
civilizations impasse requires that we
reach outside of the world's story that
we've operated so the the conspiracy
myth helps us to open to a larger world
story because it's saying things are not
as they seem and that is one of the
psychic truths that takes form in a
conspiracy theory even if the details
are not literally true that that psychic
truth is crying for attention you get
into these into these realms that are
beyond what we recognize as proven
provable or disprovable and how do we
engage those realms this is beyond the
scope of journalism it's more entering
the scope of a fiction of poetry and
fiction and poetry I think are essential
they've been kind of marginalized as
entertainment today but they are
essential organs of human knowing that
we also need to bring in so I'm I'm when
I call something a myth that is not to
devalue it I honored David Icke for his
work and Lisa Renee and all these other
people for their work in telling us a
myth and elaborating a myth in giving
some form to hidden psychic truths and
repressed social truths find it
interesting as well that these
alternative narratives these myths are
coming up in the middle of what is
effectively a really liminal space for
everyone like we just get this
of the worlds between or the the
distance between these worlds are
growing ever thinner we're in a liminal
we're all going through some kind of
liminal initiation experience in the
middle of this yeah and I think it's
gonna this is just the first step things
might go somewhat back to normal for a
little while
but we're just getting a taste of the
dissolving of what we thought was real
and permanent in normal I think I agree
Charles thank you very much for making
the time yeah
thanks David hey everyone this is a very
quick message about the rebel wisdom
festival at the end of May which was
going to be our biggest ever in-person
event with 400 people in London
obviously that's not happening now but
we've brought it online and we've made
it free for everybody two days of
rebellious ideas and profound
experiences so we still have all the
speakers that we were going to have for
the festival including Daniel Schmidt
hamburger Nora Bateson and we're also
adding new speakers all the time we've
just added Douglas rushkoff and Jamie
wheel plus a load of great facilitators
offering practices and skills to build
up sovereignty sense making and
connection so sign up at the link and
we'll see you there